Well, it's time to talk about the causes
and effects of slavery in the British
colonies. It's certainly not a fun one
to talk about, but you know, you got to
know it nonetheless. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked, let's get
to it. Okay. Now, when you think about
the geographical concentration of
slavery during the colonial period, I'm
guessing that little map inside your
brain zooms into the South and the
Caribbean. And that is not a bad
instinct, my dear pupil, but it's
certainly not the whole story. The fact
is, slavery was present in all the
British colonies of the Americas on
account of the terrific demand for labor
that produced colonial goods for export.
And it was those goods that brought in
embarrassing amounts of wealth for the
British crown. And hey, monarchs like
Charles II needed that money because, as
you may or may not know, his gaggle of
illegitimate children weren't going to
support themselves. Oh, by the way, if
you want note guys to follow along with
this video and all my videos along with
quizzes to help you remember it all,
then check that link in the description.
Anyway, the point is here are all the
British colonies in North America, and
all of them relied on slavery to some
extent. However, there is a spatial
pattern to slavery that's pretty easy to
remember. Start here in the north and
you have the fewest amount of enslaved
people and then the further you move
south the more these societies relied
upon enslaved labor. So up here in New
England recall that it was mostly made
up of small family farms since that was
really all that they could muster given
the rocky soil and the colder climate.
Therefore while some enslaved Africans
were imported to this region it was very
little by comparison. And then in the
middle colonies there were slightly more
enslaved Africans and they were
concentrated mostly in port cities like
New York and New Jersey where they
worked in the docks. Additionally, many
of the other enslaved Africans in this
region worked in households and still
others worked in large grain plantations
located in the Hudson River Valley. But
then, as we start to move into the
Chesapeake region, the amount of
enslaved Africans begins to spike
rapidly. Since we're getting into a
region where the climate is warmer and
the growing seasons are longer, that
meant that this region was dominated by
large-scale plantations that exported,
among other things, high demand crops
like tobacco. And it's the same story as
we move south through the Carolinas and
end up in the British West Indies. The
latter of which held by far the largest
concentration of enslaved Africans on
account of their deep reliance on sugar
cultivation. By the time we get down
here, the black population outnumbered
the white population 4 to1. A reality
that started to make the white planters
more than a little twitchy. And so what
they did about their twitchiness was to
ensure that they could control the
enslaved black population. And they did
that by creating a new definition of
slavery as well as imposing new laws
that aimed to keep the racial hierarchy
intact. Now, as for the new definition,
chatt slavery became the dominant form
of coerced labor in the British
colonies. Essentially, the word chatt
means property. And so, the idea is that
enslaved people were now the complete
and perpetual property of the slave
holder. Additionally, as I mentioned in
a previous video, planters in the
Caribbean adopted the Barbados slave
code, which stripped all rights from
enslaved blacks and granted white
planters complete power over them, which
led to brutal and vicious punishments
for the enslaved. And eventually, those
codes were also adopted in the southern
colonies as slavery became even more
prominent. And finally, other laws were
passed stating that if an enslaved woman
bore a child, then that child would also
be perpetually enslaved. And from there,
similar law codes were adopted in other
colonies as well. Okay, now here's where
I tell you that although enslaved
Africans constituted the main source of
labor in the British colonies by the end
of this period, it wasn't like that in
the beginning. In fact, at the beginning
of this period, the bulk of the labor
done in the colonies was performed by
indentured servants. And if that sounds
like work was done by servants with a
fresh set of false teeth, well, then no,
that's that's not what they were. No, an
indenture was basically a contract. And
so an indentured servant was a person
who was contracted to work for a certain
period of time in order to pay off a
debt. And in our case, that debt was the
cost of migrating from Great Britain to
the colonies. So for example, some guy
in Britain decides that he wants to
relocate to Virginia for work. But as it
turns out, he's so poor that when he
goes to the local pond, the ducks throw
him food. So ain't no way he can afford
passage to America. But if he signed an
indenture, then the trip will be paid
for so long as he was willing to work
without wages in the New World for seven
years in order to pay off that debt.
after which he'd go free. And as it
turns out, this arrangement was pretty
attractive to a lot of men who migrated
to the American colonies. And it's going
to be important for you to know that at
this point, both black and white workers
were indentured servants. However,
around the middle of the 17th century,
the race line would begin to thicken
significantly. For example, in 1640, a
black indentured servant named John
Punch ran away from his plantation along
with two white indentured servants. And
when they were captured, the white men
received four more years on their
indenture. But Punch was condemned to
lifelong slavery. So, this event
signaled a significant shift toward
race-based slavery in Virginia and
throughout the rest of the colonies.
Anyway, one of the chief reasons
indentured servitude was attractive was
because at the end of the contract, the
worker would receive a plot of land that
they could work for themselves. But in
the second half of the 17th century,
this system began to break down in
Virginia since the land available to
freed becoming far more scarce. As it
turned out, when you worked for seven
years in order to get your own plot of
land and there isn't much left, well,
you know, that would make anybody a
little saucy. So, a group of these
disgruntled indentured servants started
causing some trouble. And in response,
Virginia's governor, William Berkeley,
led the legislature to revoke these
men's voting rights. And as a result, a
group of these disenfranchised farmers
led by Nathaniel Bacon erupted in
fighting. Now, a significant part of
their beef with Berkeley was that they
felt he was favoring the Virginia elite
and refusing to help farmers on the
frontier attack indigenous people in
order to expand their landoldings. So,
first they attacked American Indian
settlements and then they came for
Berkeley himself, who courageously fled
like a chump. Now, there were lots of
twists and turns, but in the end, Bacon
got sick and died. And that gave
Berkeley the opportunity to crush the
rebellion, which he did swiftly. And the
whole reason I'm telling you this story
is because this one event, perhaps more
than any other in this period, led to a
dramatic shift in the labor systems in
the American colonies. Now, prior to
this, there were definitely enslaved
Africans in the colonies, but most of
the work in the Chesapeake region was
carried out by indentured servants. But
this rebellion made wealthy southern
planters clutch their pearls because
they feared other groups of disgruntled
endangered servants inciting even more
rebellions. And of special importance
here was the fact that both free and
enslaved black people participated in
Bacon's rebellion. There was really no
color line here in this event. The only
thing that these rebels had in common
was that they were poor and disgruntled.
And so the slave codes and the various
race-based laws that I mentioned earlier
had an added benefit for wealthy
planters. Namely, that black people were
now considered to be less than white
people of any level of wealth. And that
helped ensure that poor whites and
blacks would be unlikely to unite again
in rebellion since even the poorest of
whites could hold on to the belief that
at least they were better than someone.
Anyway, from this point on, planters
began to demand more and more enslaved
Africans, which as I mentioned would
become the dominant labor system in the
South. Now, I confess it's a little
weird that I even have to say this, but
enslaved Africans who were made to
endure the brutality of this system did
not enjoy or even appreciate being
enslaved. But I do have to say because
there's this persistent misunderstanding
that many, if not all, enslaved laborers
were content with their lot in life,
especially if they had the good fortune
to labor for that mythical good master.
But as we say here in the South, that
dog won't hunt. Now, all you have to do
is look at the abundance of newspaper
ads announcing the escape of enslaved
people during that era, and it's clear
that these enslaved laborers were not
the least content with their situation.
But even more than that, we have several
examples of slave resistance, which is
an equally important part of this whole
story. The first way they resisted this
brutal system was through covert means,
which is to say, these acts were smaller
and more secretive. For example,
enslaved people attempted to maintain
their family structures in secret even
though they were under the constant
threat of separation if a planter
decided to sell one or the other members
of the family. Or sometimes they worked
slower or broke tools, both of which
were ways to hinder the progress of the
plantation, even if only subtly.
Additionally, many enslaved Africans
worked hard to resist the dehumanizing
effects of slavery by maintaining
cultural elements that they carried from
their ancestral home. things like gender
roles and religious beliefs and their
own traditional languages out of the
hearing of their white masters.
Additionally, they introduced musical
instruments like drums and the banjo to
the Americas. And by blending African,
European, and indigenous traditions,
they created syncric cultures that
resulted in foods like gumbo and
jumbalaya and traditions like martyr.
And while covert resistance was much
more widespread among the entire
enslaved population, it was overt
resistance which had a much bigger
impact. Now, the first slave rebellion
in the 18th century occurred in New York
City. A group of enslaved people
intentionally burned down a building at
the edge of town. And as white folks
came rushing to see what was going on,
rebels killed nine of them. Now, those
rebels were pretty quickly captured and
tortured and publicly burned in the town
square. But it was a sure signal that
these enslaved workers were fed up with
the ravages of slavery. And then down in
Jamaica, which was a major cash cow for
Britain owing to its prodigious exports
of sugar, another rebellion broke out
here. The resistance was led by fugitive
slave who lived in what were known as
maroon societies. And they basically
waged war against British planters for
more than a decade until finally the
British signed a treaty recognizing
their freedom in 1740. And then the most
famous of all slave rebellions in the 13
colonies was known as the Stono
Rebellion which occurred in South
Carolina in 1739. Basically a small
group of recently arrived enslaved
people to South Carolina gathered by the
Stoneo River and launched an attack
throughout the region. And the further
they marched, the more numbers they
gained until the rebels were about 100
strong. They killed any white people
that they came across and burned their
houses and barns as well. Now,
eventually the South Carolina militia
met the rebels in battle and quickly
defeated them. But what's most important
to remember about this rebellion and the
numerous other rebellions that occurred
around the same time is this. The chief
effect of slave rebellions was to drive
fear deep into the hearts of southern
planters that their own enslaved people
would revolt. Therefore, South
Carolina's slave codes were made even
more severe in order to suppress any
future rebellions. All of which is to
say the institution of slavery became
even more entrenched in the southern
colonies and even more brutal toward
those who are made to endure it. Okay,
you can click here to watch my other
unit 2 videos or you can click here to
grab my video note guides which are
going to help you get all the contents
of this course firmly crammed into your
brain fold. And I appreciate you coming
around and I'll catch you on the
flipflop. Himler out.